Let's start with a quick bit of background of how UNIX was implemented before ZOS.
The name OpenEdition was used when the support was introduced.
At that time, IBM didn't have the right to call it UNIX.
The term OpenEdition is still seen in some documentation, but IBM does now have the
right to the word UNIX after the full UNIX branding was obtained in 1996.
The ZOS UNIX support is now known as UNIX system services and is often called USS.
When this UNIX support became available, the role of an MVS system changed.
This opened up new opportunities for MVS, OS390 and now ZOS.
UNIX applications can be ported from other UNIX environments to run on ZOS UNIX system
services.
However, porting might not be trivial.
There's the problem of ASCII and EBCDIC, which must be addressed and we'll get to
that later, believe me.
But first of all, let's see how workstation users can get access to ZOS applications and
data.
With ZOS UNIX, workstation users can access traditional MVS applications and data, as
well as POSIX and XPG 4.2 conforming applications and data on ZOS.
This diagram shows that a workstation application using Motif and XWindows can access data on
a ZOS system.
Motif refers to both a graphical user interface specification and the widget toolkit for building
applications that follow that specification under the XWindows system on UNIX operating
systems.
The XWindows system is the underlying graphic system on all modern UNIX systems.
XWindows provides the facilities to accept input from a mouse and keyboard and the ability
to draw graphical objects to a computer screen.
It's supported by all major workstation vendors.
XWindows is a TCPIP application and comes as part of the TCPIP product for ZOS.
The box on the picture that contains the XWindows client in the diagram symbolizes
the XWindows API on ZOS.
Now let's see how high-speed storage devices on Z can be useful for workstations.
The DFSMS-MVS product on ZOS provides data administration functions like backup and archiving
of data on a ZOS system.
With ZOS UNIX, DFSMS-MVS can be used to backup and archive the hierarchical file system.
A workstation application might be moved to ZOS if backup is critical.
An alternative solution is to use the Tivoli storage manager product on ZOS which can periodically
upload data on the workstation and archive it on the host.
Either way, folks want to use the same tools and applications to backup and restore individual
ZOS UNIX files residing in a ZOS file system, as they will do with any other ZOS datasets.
Another solution is to backup and restore individual ZOS UNIX files residing in something
called ZFS is integrated into existing DFSMS-HSM backup and recovery and DFSMS-DSS dump and
restore capability, allowing for centralized data management across the ZOS platform.
Now ZOS is well-suited to be a server for batch applications because of its large processing
capability, high-speed printers and high reliability and availability.
Large batch applications can be moved from a workstation to ZOS.
ZOS UNIX shell scripts which are similar to RexxXX can run in the shell session or they
can be submitted as a ZOS batch job.
BPX batch is a utility that you can use to run shell commands or executable files through
the batch facility.
You can invoke BPX batch from a batch job or from the TSLE environment as a command through
the call command or from a C list or a RexxXEC.
So we've seen some of the opportunities and some of the new ways to use ZOS with ZOS UNIX.
Let's look at two exploiters of these facilities which are IBM HTTP server and IBM WebSphere
application server.
Both of these provide a web server environment for ZOS.
This server is a standard compliant product which requires ZOS UNIX and its file system.
It uses the POSIX threading standard, enabling one server to handle multiple client requests.
The homepages stored on ZOS reside in the hierarchical file system or a ZOS-PDS or PDSE.
There are also services and samples provided to show access from a web browser through the
ZOS WebSphere and Liberty servers to Kix and DB2 data.
This is a way to bring your order transaction and processing applications to new users through
the internet.
In the next video, we'll take a look at the components of ZOS.